<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tech | Bitwise Evolution]]></title>
  <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://creswick.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-11-09T16:19:24-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://creswick.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rogan Creswick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing custom XSessions in Fedora 15]]></title>
    <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/2011/11/07/xmonad-in-fedora-15/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-07T17:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://creswick.github.com/blog/2011/11/07/xmonad-in-fedora-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I realized today that Fedora 15 doesn't expose a UI for selecting
another xsession by default -- you can only log into Gnome 3.
Thankfully, once you install another window manager, then the
selection widget does appear; however, it was not clear how to add a
WM that wasn't packaged with Fedora.</p>

<p>In my case, I wanted to run the latest development version of
<a href="http://xmonad.org">xmonad</a>.  (Queue about an hour of fruitless
Googling.)</p>

<p>Eventually, I broke down and <code>yum install fluxbox</code>'d to get an
example.  After that, a <code>repoquery --list fluxbox</code> gave a list of the
files installed, and pointed me to <code>/usr/share/xsessions</code>, which
contains the list of WMs that the Fedora greeter uses to present
options.</p>

<p>Adding a new option is as simple as creating a new desktop file in
that directory, and pointing the <code>Exec</code> field to the binary of your
WM.</p>

<p>eg:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ cd /usr/share/xsessions/
$ cat xmonad.desktop
[Desktop Entry]
Name=XMonad
Comment=Tiling window manager
Exec=/home/creswick/development/xmonad/cabal-dev/bin/xmonad
Type=Application
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging with Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/2011/10/31/blogging-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-31T12:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://creswick.github.com/blog/2011/10/31/blogging-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I heard about <a href="octopress.org">Octopress</a> today, so I'm giving it a
shot.  It uses github pages to provide a blogging platform, which I've wanted for a while.</p>

<p>This post is just testing to see how Octopress works (I'm putting it through it's paces.)</p>

<p>``` bash Testing bash syntax highlighting http://www.haller.ws/logs/view.cgi/WhatAreShellsGoodFor haller's tips.</p>

<h1>Works much like xargs, but don't forget the flexibility of inserting</h1>

<h1>{} in the ensuing expression for the $line location.</h1>

<p>#</p>

<h1>Examples: http://www.haller.ws/logs/view.cgi/LearnToShootWithBash</h1>

<p>each() {</p>

<pre><code>local line="" 
while read line; do # sub {} with $line and run it 
</code></pre>

<h1>eval "${@/{}/${line}}"</h1>

<pre><code>    eval "${@/\{\}/\"${line}\"}" # $@ =~ s/ {} / $line /
done 
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Here's another code block, using Haskell:</p>

<p>``` haskell Does it understand Haskell?</p>

<p>-- Some random code from Newt:
import Test.HUnit      ( (@=?) )
import Test.Framework.Providers.HUnit
import Test.Framework ( testGroup, Test )</p>

<p>-- | Create a Test from a function, a description, an input, and an oracle:
genTest :: (Show a, Show b, Eq b) => (a -> b) -> (String, a, b) -> Test
genTest fn (descr, input, oracle) =</p>

<pre><code>testCase (descr++" input: "++show input) assert
    where assert = oracle @=? fn input
</code></pre>

<p>genTestIO :: (Show a, Show b, Eq b) => (a -> IO b) -> (String, a, b) -> Test
genTestIO fn (descr, input, oracle) =</p>

<pre><code>testCase (descr++" input: " ++show input) $ do
    res &lt;- fn input
    oracle @=? res
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>There are more examples of including code here: http://octopress.org/docs/blogging/code/</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prezi: scalable, navigable presentations]]></title>
    <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/2010/10/06/prezi-scalable-navigable-presentations/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://creswick.github.com/blog/2010/10/06/prezi-scalable-navigable-presentations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Edit:</strong>Prezi now has support for customizing colors / themes, and even documentation for the css! <a href="http://prezi.com/learn/color-wizard/?utm_source=MadMimi&utm_medium=email&utm_content=Holiday+features:+colors+and+fonts,+drag+and+drop&utm_campaign=Introducing+Colors,+Fonts,+and+Snap&utm_term=customize"> I'm happy to see official support for these features, but the layout problems are still a show-stopper for me.<strong>/Edit</strong></p>

<p>I have been adopting a presentation style that diverges from the traditional bullet-point style promoted by Open Office and PowerPoint (although, PowerPoint 2007 diverges from pure bullets to more interesting shapes, using shading and encapsulation to show hierarchy.  It's a large improvement, but it still falls short of my ideal).  Instead of bullets and text, I try to make use of imagery and visual examples whenever possible.</p>

<p>My experience has reinforced what I've come across in the literature about balancing your audience's attention between the content on the wall and your narration.  Too much text or detail and you risk loosing your audience because they're overwhelmed or, if you're lucky, because they are focusing on the slide content instead of listening to your explanations.  It is also much easier to trigger emotional responses with visuals than it is with text, which explains some of the motivation for promotional/motivational presentations that are virtually devoid of text.  (<a href="http://www.sethgodin.com/">Seth Godin's</a> talks come to mind.  One way in which my presentations differ substantially from Seth's is that I generally talk about fairly technical topics.  The difficulties associated with finding high-quality, emotional, images to convey the intricate details of <tt>ptrace(2)</tt> is not the topic of this post, however.)</p>

<p>A number of years back, I found a mention of using Scalable Vector Graphics (SVGs) for unconstrained presentations and that idea has stuck.  I've been developing slides in PowerPoint (OpenOffice has not yet reached the point where I can create professional-looking content), but I've never been happy with the traditional slide-based presentation style.  SVGs promise the ability to move between arbitrary locations, following a pre-defined path from "slide" to "slide".  Furthermore, since the content is scalable, you can literally zoom in to a portion of content to go into more detail, or zoom out to show context.  This presentation mode would also make it easy to diverge from your plan based on audience feedback.  This <em>can</em> be done with PowerPoint, but it is extremely difficult.</p>

<p><a href="http://prezi.com">Prezi</a> promises these benefits, so I spent the last few days building a presentation with Prezi at Galois: <a href="http://www.galois.com/blog/2010/09/30/tech-talk-enabling-portable-build-systems/">portable build systems</a>.  (The prezi presentation is near the bottom of this post.)  The rest of this entry discusses my experiences with Prezi.</p>

<h2>The Good, the Bad and the Ugly</h2>

<p>I initially found the Prezi interface to be very intuitive.  The translation "zebra", a stripped round mult-function circle, appears whenever you select an object.  You then use the zebra to move, scale, rotate, or otherwise manipulate the selected object.  Other options are presented through a bubble menu that rotates and scales to show more detailed options as you select sub "bubbles".  It is well worth the few minutes it takes to sign up for a free account and try it out.  If you happen to be using 64-bit linux, you probably won't be able to use the flash app, however.  Prezi doesn't appear to work under that environment.  (if you can interact with the presentation embedded on this page, then you should be Ok.)  There is also an Adobe Air-based desktop app, which I used extensively.</p>

<p>I was off and brainstorming a presentation mind-map style after only a few minutes playing with the interface.  The freedom to create a few words of text, zoom in and flesh out more details, jump back out and pull in an image, all without concern for the layout of final form of the presentation was extremely motivating and liberating.</p>

<p>I was able to be quite productive with Prezi until I began to consider the need for a unifying theme.  Two things stood in the way:</p>

<ol>
<li>Only eight options were provided for the overall look and feel of the presentation, and none were close enough to the Galois color scheme. There is also no way to add new look and feel options, and each option changes all the colors, fonts, backgrounds, and general style of the presentation.</li>
<li>The set of shapes and drawing tools is very limited. You can create: Thin free-hand lines, thick free-hand "highlighter" lines, circular rings (round frames), square brackets (square frames), gradient-filled rounded rectangles (roundrect frames), arrows, text in one of three fonts (optionally with bullets).
</ol>


<p>None of the pre-defined colors can be changed through the user interface, aside from the eight styles mentioned above, which change <em>all</em> the colors / styles and fonts.  You can include arbitrary images, which helps with the limited set of shapes, however, you can only include pdfs if you are using the web-based client, the desktop client does not currently support pdf importing.</p>

<p>I stumbled across a solution to the limited selection of colors by unzipping the .pez file that holds a Prezi presentation on-disk and exploring the contents:
<code lang="bash">
prezi/
├── content.xml
├── preview.png
└── repo/</p>

<pre><code>├── 13177749.png
├── 13177754.jpg
├── 13177758.png
├── 13177835.swf
├── codetree.png
└── Personal_computer,_exploded_5.png
</code></pre>

<p></code>
content.xml defines the SVG-like presentation content, and it ends with a set of css styles:
<code lang="html"></p>



<p></code>
The colors in these styles can be adjusted, and you can even add new styles here (although you will need to manually insert them into the xml where you wish to use the new styles).  After editing the content.xml, zip up the presentation tree, taking care to maintain the correct hierarchy and no compression:
<code lang="bash">
$ ls
prezi/
$ zip -r -0 enabling-portable-build-systems-biuinv2vus9x.pez prezi/
</code>
One surprising benefit is that the updated styles are actually adopted by the UI widgets in the Prezi application, once you load a modified .pez file.</p>

<p><a href="http://blog.ciscavate.org/wp-content/2010/10/prezi-text.png" style="text-align:center;" ><img src="http://blog.ciscavate.org/wp-content/2010/10/prezi-text.png" alt="The &quot;Title | Title | Body&quot; buttons change according to the css stylesheet in content.xml." title="prezi-text" width="300" style="margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;"/></a></p>

<p>These changes also persist across saves, loads, uploading to Prezi.com, and they appear to render properly when embedded, granting quite a lot of power, if you're able and willing to work with xml and css periodically.</p>

<p>Editing content.xml also proved to be the best way to spellcheck the presentation content, although the text that is actually <em>displayed</em> is in CDATA nodes, which your editor may skip over when running a spell checker.  Thankfully, the text is duplicated as plain text nodes, so you are still alerted to spelling errors when running ispell-buffer in emacs.  You can then fix the CDATA entry with a recursive edit.  (I suspect that the duplication is there to simplify text searching.)</p>

<p>I'm rather satisfied with these workarounds: The ugly aspects could be automated with some simple tools to update the content.xml as needed, and the hacks I found worked surprisingly well.</p>

<h2>Background images and "refactoring"</h2>

<p>Unfortunately, I don't think Prezi is ready for prime-time, despite my success with css styles and spellchecking.  There are simply no facilities to precisely align or distribute objects with respect to each-other.  Further complicating this is the lack of a <a href="http://community.prezi.com/prezi/topics/grouping_as_in_cntrl_g">"group" option</a> to create aggregate objects.  You can select multiple objects by dragging a rectangle if you hold shift, but that isn't possible if the objects are on top of other objects -- the first click of a shift-drag must occur on the background of the Prezi, or you will simply select the lower object.  While this sounds a bit like a minor quibble, it is impossible to accurately position complex sets of objects if they are layered on top of other content (such as a background image).  I often need to add or remove "slides", and with Prezi, that can include a lot of object translations to provide or absorb space while fitting with the high-level overview of your presentation.  Without alignment tools, you also take the risk that a title will display askew with respect to the screen borders when you are mid-presentation.</p>

<p>I eventually adopted the following practice to help keep content square:</p>

<ul>
<li>Press 'space' to enter "show" mode, and position the screen as it would be to show the "slide", then pres 'space' again to return to edit mode.</li>
<li>Create a roundrect frame, it will be square with the current view.</li>
<li>Use the borders of the roundrect as visual guides to make the slide content as square as possible.  I usually place the baseline of the title text with the top of the roundrect and then position it after the angle has been fixed.</li>
<li>Delete the roundrect</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, never rotate any individual components of that slide again.  Use shift-clicking to select everything in the slide each time you need to rotate or move the slide.  If you need to add new content, first enter 'show' mode and click on the frame to make the camera rotate properly with respect to the slide.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I'm excited to see how Prezi evolves, and I will be one of the first in line once the selection / alignment problems are fixed.  I hope that Prezi will motivate other implementations with similar capabilities, there is plenty of room for some healthy competition.</p>

<div class="prezi-player"><style type="text/css" media="screen">.prezi-player { width: 550px; } .prezi-player-links { text-align: center; }</style><object id="prezi_biuinv2vus9x" name="prezi_biuinv2vus9x" classid="clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000" width="550" height="400"><param name="movie" value="http://prezi.com/bin/preziloader.swf"/><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true"/><param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"/><param name="bgcolor" value="#ffffff"/><param name="flashvars" value="prezi_id=biuinv2vus9x&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;autoplay=no&amp;autohide_ctrls=0"/><embed id="preziEmbed_biuinv2vus9x" name="preziEmbed_biuinv2vus9x" src="http://prezi.com/bin/preziloader.swf" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" allowscriptaccess="always" width="550" height="400" bgcolor="#ffffff" flashvars="prezi_id=biuinv2vus9x&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;color=ffffff&amp;autoplay=no&amp;autohide_ctrls=0"></embed></object><div class="prezi-player-links"><p><a title="Galois is developing build system configuration capabilities to improve the portability of build systems." href="http://prezi.com/biuinv2vus9x/enabling-portable-build-systems/">Enabling Portable Build Systems</a> on <a href="http://prezi.com">Prezi</a></p></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recovered Puzzles]]></title>
    <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/2010/07/26/recovered-puzzles/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://creswick.github.com/blog/2010/07/26/recovered-puzzles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I used to collect puzzles--back when I had a wiki to post them to--but that content was lost to me a few years ago when the system hosting my personal content had a slew of hard drive issues.  I was lamenting that loss last week when a coworker suggested that I could possibly find the content on the way-back machine at <a href="http://www.archive.org">archive.org</a>, and indeed, I did!</p>

<p>Without further ado, here's a short list of brainteasers (none are of my creation, and I do not have citations--if you know who to credit for any of these, please let me know and I will add proper attribution info.)</p>

<p><strong>Calendar Cubes</strong></p>

<p>A man has two cubes on his desk. Each face of each cube has a single-digit number wirtten on it. With these two cubes, the man is able to enumerate all the days in any month, and each morning he arranges the cubes so that the number of the current day is on top, <em>always</em> using both cubes. How are the numbers distributed on the cubes?</p>

<p><strong>Pennies 1</strong></p>

<p>You are blindfolded in a room with 100 pennies. 30 of the pennies are heads-up, the remainder are tails-up. You can interact with the pennies in any way, but your fingers are not dexterous enough to feel the contours of the coins (so you can't feel one to see which side is heads, or tails). Since you are blindfolded, you can't see them either. Your task is to manipulate the coins such that there are two sets and each set has an equal number of coins that are heads-up. (The sets must be disjoint, non-empty, and all pennies must be in one of the two sets.)</p>

<p><strong>Pennies 2</strong></p>

<p>Given N pennies, one of which is counterfiet (and therefore is of different weight from the remainder) and a balance, how can you find the counterfeit coin in less three weighings on the balance.</p>

<p><strong>Eggs</strong></p>

<p>You are in a 100-floor building on a planet with oddly low gravity and/or surprisingly durable eggs.  You happen to have two of these eggs (unfertilized, I assure you). Your task is to find the highest floor from which you can drop an egg and have it remain intact.</p>

<p><strong>Numbers</strong></p>

<p>Given 99 unique integers between 1 and 100, provide an optimal algorithm to find the remaining integer in that range that is not in the set.</p>

<p>Hint: Bcgvzny gnxrf yvarne gvzr naq pbafgnag fcnpr.</p>

<p><strong>Prisoners</strong></p>

<p>50 people are inprisioned, and during their imprisonment the captor will invite people randomly in to visit with her. All visits are one-on-one, and each prisoner has a unique tunnel from their cell to the captor's office (so you can't look out your cell and see who is going in). In the captor's room is a bowl that the prisoners can optionally turn over, or turn right-side up during their visit(s). The initial state of the bowl is known to everyone.</p>

<p>The imprisonment may last for an infinite period of time, during which each prisoner will be invited into the captor's office many, many times (essentially infinite, but it needs not be infinite, it could just be a reasonably small number in the optimal case). The imprisonment ends when one prisoner says: "Everyone has been in to see the captor at least once." If a prisoner says this and they are wrong, all prisoners are killed immediately. Because the captor may decide not to visit anyone for a while, it is as if the prisoners have no concept of time, so they can't bound the number of people seen based on the passage of time.</p>

<p>To give the prisoners a chance, they are allowed to convene briefly before their imprisonment, during which time they can plan a strategy. How do they do it?</p>

<p><strong>Sequences</strong>
What is the next line in this sequence?</p>

<pre>
1
1 1
2 1
1 1 1 2
3 1 1 2
2 1 1 2 1 3
</pre>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test-Driven XML Schema dev with xmlstarlet]]></title>
    <link href="http://creswick.github.com/blog/2009/10/17/test-driven-xml-schema-dev-with-xmlstarlet/"/>
    <updated>2009-10-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://creswick.github.com/blog/2009/10/17/test-driven-xml-schema-dev-with-xmlstarlet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just to document how I do this:</p>

<p><em>Problem:</em> I need a schema for FooTask</p>

<p><em>Solution:</em></p>

<ul>
<li> Create a 'tests' directory.</li>
<li> populate said directory with simple example xml files.</li>
<li> Name those files <code>valid-foo.xml</code> or <code>invalid-bar.xml</code> (I use numbers for foo and bar).</li>
<li> Create your xsd file in the same directory as 'tests'. Lets call it <code>foo.xsd</code></li>
<li>  Copy the following Makefile into the same location.</li>
</ul>


<p>[cc lang="bash"]
XSD=foo.xsd</p>

<h1>run xmlstarlet with -e to see verbose error.</h1>

<p>test:</p>

<pre><code>@for file in `ls -1 tests/valid*.xml`; do if xmlstarlet val -q --xsd ${XSD} $${file}; then echo "pass"; else echo "fail: $${file}"; fi; done
@for file in `ls -1 tests/invalid*.xml`; do if ! xmlstarlet val -q --xsd ${XSD} $${file}; then echo "pass"; else echo "fail: $${file}"; fi; done
</code></pre>

<p>[/cc]</p>

<p>Now, run make, and if anything fails you can manually run <code>xmlstarlet val -e --xsd foo.xsh [failing file.xml]</code> to see the details.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
